<pre>

    <b>The
        <em>&lt;config&gt;</em> element is a nested element of
        <stepref name="webtest"/> and is used
		to configure the target host system to use for a particular webtest and several other feature like
		reporting of test results and printing of debug information.
    </b>

    <b>Since the
        <em>&lt;config&gt;</em> element can contain so many different attributes,
		the description of the attributes is split over many tables.
    </b>

    <b>The first table describes the default URL parameter.</b>

        <attributes>
            <attribute>
                <name>host</name>
                <description>Defines the hostname to use for executing requests, e.g.
                    &quot;localhost&quot; or &quot;www.myhost.com&quot;.</description>
                <required>No, default is &quot;localhost&quot;</required>
            </attribute>
            <attribute>
                <name>port</name>
                <description>Defines the port number to use for executing requests, e.g.
                    &quot;8080&quot;.</description>
                <required>No, defaults is &quot;80&quot;</required>
            </attribute>
            <attribute>
                <name>protocol</name>
                <description>Defines the protocol to use for executing requests.
                    &quot;http&quot;, &quot;https&quot;, and &quot;file&quot; are currently the only supported protocols.</description>
                <required>No, defaults is &quot;http&quot;</required>
            </attribute>
            <attribute>
                <name>basepath</name>
                <description>Defines the constant base path used to construct request URLs, e.g. &quot;shop&quot;
		can be considered a
                    <em>basepath</em> in &quot;http:/www.myhost.com/shop/productlist&quot;
		and &quot;http:/www.myhost.com/shop/checkout&quot;.
                </description>
                <required>No, defaults is empty</required>
            </attribute>
        </attributes>
    <b>
	    The next table describes the attributes responsible for WebTest's reporting and logging.
        These attributes define
        <em>if</em> and
        <em>where</em> WebTest store logging information. Actual reporting is usually
			performed by xsl transformation after the test complete.
    </b>
        <attributes>
            <attribute>
                <name>summary</name>
                <description>Deprecated: not used anymore.</description>
            </attribute>
            <attribute>
                <name>saveresponse</name>
                <description>Defines whether the last response received from the target
                host is saved into the file &quot;&lt;saveprefix&gt;&lt;uniqueId&gt;.html&quot;.
                <em>saveprefix</em> is the value set in the &lt;saveprefix&gt; config element.<n/>
                <em>uniqueId</em> is a timestamp at the time the file is saved.<n/>
                This is especially helpful for debugging your tests.
                </description>
                <required>No, default is &quot;false&quot;</required>
            </attribute>
            <attribute>
                <name>saveprefix</name>
                <description>Sets the name to use if the current response received from the target
                host is to be saved into a file. A unique id will also be appended after the prefix.
                </description>
                <required>No, default is &quot;response&quot;</required>
            </attribute>
            <attribute>
                <name>resultpath</name>
                <description>Defines the resultpath of saved responses (for example last response).</description>
                <required>No, default is the subdirectory &quot;webtest-results&quot; of the project base directory.</required>
            </attribute>
            <attribute>
                <name>resultfile</name>
                <description>Deprecated: not used anymore.
                </description>
            </attribute>
        </attributes>
    <b>The next table describes the webtest's behaviour when encountering failures and errors.</b>
        <attributes>
            <attribute>
                <name>haltonerror</name>
                <description>Determines if the execution of the current &lt;webtest&gt; stops if a
		program error (unhandled exception) is encountered in one of the test steps. An
                    <key>ANT</key> BuildFailed exception will be raised
		if it is set to &quot;Yes&quot;. This will terminate the execution of the
                    <key>ANT</key> script.
                    <n/>
		Setting the option to &quot;false&quot; will stop the execution of the current &lt;webtest&gt; but continues with the
		next
                    <key>ANT</key> task, e.g. another &lt;webtest&gt;.
                </description>
                <required>No, default is &quot;true&quot;</required>
            </attribute>
            <attribute>
                <name>errorproperty</name>
                <description>Specifies the name of an ant property which is set to true if the execution
					of the current &lt;webtest&gt; stops if a program error (unhandled exception) is encountered
					in one of the test steps. When using this property, set &quot;haltonerror&quot; to &quot;false&quot;.
					Then check the ant property after performing all of your tests and if set fail. This allows your tests to
					continue running even if some experience execution errors (allowing you to catch multiple errors with one test run)
					but still ultimately fails the build if anything went wrong.
                </description>
                <required>No</required>
            </attribute>
            <attribute>
                <name>haltonfailure</name>
                <description>Determines if the execution of the current test halts if a failure of one of the
		test steps is detected, e.g. a &lt;verify...&gt; test did not pass. Even when set to &quot;false&quot;
		all of the trailing &lt;step&gt;s of the current &lt;webtest&gt; will be skipped but processing will
		continue with the next &lt;webtest&gt;.</description>
                <required>No, default is &quot;true&quot;</required>
            </attribute>
            <attribute>
                <name>failureproperty</name>
                <description>Specifies the name of an ant property which is set to true if the test fails.
					When using this property, set &quot;haltonfailure&quot; to &quot;false&quot;. Then check the
					ant property after performing all of your tests and if set fail. This allows your tests to
					continue running even if some fail (allowing you to catch multiple errors with one test run)
					but still ultimately fails the build if anything went wrong.
                </description>
                <required>No</required>
            </attribute>
        </attributes>
    <b>The next table groups miscellaneous configuration options.
    </b>
        <attributes>
            <attribute>
                <name>browser</name>
                <description>Specifies the browser that should be simulated.
                Allowed values are 
                <example>Firefox3</example> (or <example>FF3</example>) (deprecated),
                <example>Firefox3.6</example> (or <example>FF3.6</example>),
                <example>Firefox10</example> (or <example>FF10</example>),
                <example>InternetExplorer6</example> (or <example>IE6</example>),
                <example>InternetExplorer7</example> (or <example>IE7</example>),
                <example>InternetExplorer8</example> (or <example>IE8</example>).
                </description>
                <required>No, default is &quot;InternetExplorer6&quot;</required>
            </attribute>
            <attribute>
                <name>useInsecureSSL</name>
                <description>Specifies if WebTest should ignore insecure SSL certificates like self signed certificate that
                have not been added to the truststore or expired certificates.
                </description>
                <required>No, default is &quot;false&quot;</required>
            </attribute>
            <attribute>
                <name>sslKeyStore</name>
                <description>Specifies a file system path or URL to a keystore or certificate file containing one or more
                    client certificates. If present, WebTest is performing ssl authentication using client certificates.
                    The file / keystore type is defined by &quot;sslKeyStoreType&quot;.
                </description>
                <required>No, default is &quot;null&quot;</required>
            </attribute>
            <attribute>
                <name>sslKeyStoreType</name>
                <description>Specifies type of the keystore or ssl certificate file defined by &quot;sslKeyStore&quot;.
                    Can be &quot;pkcs12&quot; or &quot;jks&quot; (Java Key Store) ...
                </description>
                <required>No, default is &quot;jks&quot;</required>
            </attribute>
            <attribute>
                <name>sslKeyStorePassword</name>
                <description>Specifies the keystore password.
                </description>
                <required>No, default is &quot;null&quot;</required>
            </attribute>
            <attribute>
                <name>sslTrustStore</name>
                <description>Specifies the path or URL to a Java Key Store containing server certificates to be trusted.
                </description>
                <required>No, default is &quot;null&quot;</required>
            </attribute>
            <attribute>
                <name>sslTrustStorePassword</name>
                <description>Specifies the sslTrustStore password.
                </description>
                <required>No, default is &quot;null&quot;</required>
            </attribute>
            <attribute>
                <name>timeout</name>
                <description>Defines the timeout value in seconds for both connection and socket.<n/>
                The connection timeout is the maximum allowed time until a connection is etablished.
                The socket timeout is the timeout for waiting for data.<n/>
                A timeout value of zero is interpreted as an infinite timeout.
                </description>
                <required>No, default is &quot;300&quot;</required>
            </attribute>
            <attribute>
                <name>showhtmlparseroutput</name>
                <description>Defines that the JTidy output of parsing resulting
                    <key>HTML</key> pages shall be shown.
		If enabled, the generated errors/warnings are collected as test step parameters and written into the report file.
        The output is also written to stdout. The parser output can be used to
		detect invalid
                    <key>HTML</key> code in a particular page, unbalanced elements or invalid
		nesting of elements (e.g. &lt;form&gt; and &lt;table&gt;).
                    <n/>
		Since the parser can generate a lot of warnings and these warnings need to be
		manually analyzed, it is recommended to enable this option only on demand,
		e.g. to initially verify the correctness of an
                    <key>HTML</key> page or if a particular
		test case does not work (e.g. a button can not be found in a page).
                </description>
                <required>No, default is &quot;false&quot;</required>
            </attribute>
            <attribute>
                <name>defaultpropertytype</name>
                <description>Determines the default storage used for properties. If set to &quot;dynamic&quot;, webtest dynamic properties are used.
					If set to &quot;ant&quot;, properties are stored as ant variables. If set to &quot;antstrict&quot;, ant properties are
					used but normal ant immutability is respected, i.e. if a property is already set, then it won't be over-written.
                    <n/>
					When setting this attribute to &quot;ant&quot; or &quot;antstrict&quot;, the #{propName} syntax allows late binding
					to ant properties whereas the ${propName} syntax remains supported with normal binding.
                    <n/>
					If using ant properties to store webtest properties, the values of properties persist across &lt;webtest> tasks but
					you run the risk of name clashes with other tasks using ant properties.
                    <n/>
					If using repeat steps, avoid using &quot;antstrict&quot; for this setting if you need access to the repeat loop
					counter value. The repeat loop will execute as normal but the #{count} property will remain unchanged once set.
                </description>
                <required>No, default is &quot;dynamic&quot;,</required>
            </attribute>
            <attribute>
                <name>autorefresh</name>
                <description>Specifies whether the client should automatically follow page refresh requests (html:
                    <em>&lt;meta http-equiv="refresh" ...&gt;</em>).
                    <n/>
                    If set to "true" or "false", this indicates if refresh requests should be followed or not.
                    If set to an integer value only refresh request with a delay less or equal to the specified value will be executed. 
                </description>
                <required>No, default is &quot;false&quot;</required>
            </attribute>
        </attributes>

    <code caption="config">
        <include src='examples/configExample.xml' />
    </code>

    <b>The previous test code example will create URLs with the following prefix: "http://www.myhost.com:8080/shop/".</b>
</pre>
