<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE references SYSTEM "manpage.dtd">
<references>
    <ref id="CWT" title="Canoo WebTest" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://webtest.canoo.com/webtest"/>
        <note>The Canoo WebTest distribution.</note>
        <note>An Open Source tool to facilitate automatic functional testing
            of html-bound web applications.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="mailingList" title="Canoo WebTest Mailing List" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://lists.canoo.com/mailman/listinfo/webtest"/>
        <link href="news://news.gmane.org/gmane.comp.web.canoo.webtest"/>
        <note>The Canoo WebTest moderated mailing list for community discussions and latest news.</note>
        <note>The right place to post success stories, bugs and feature requests.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="WebTestCommunity" title="Canoo WebTest Community Site" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://webtest-community.canoo.com"/>
        <note>The Canoo WebTest Community Site for FAQ,
            sharing Contributions, Discussions, etc.</note>
        <note>A Forum-like Wiki specialized on code sharing.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="Maven" title="Maven" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://maven.apache.org/"/>
        <note>Maven is a Java project management and project comprehension tool that
            provides a well defined model for your project.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="MavenPlugin" title="Maven Canoo WebTest Plugin" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://maven-plugins.sourceforge.net/maven-webtest-plugin/index.html"/>
        <link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/turbine/maven/"/>
        <note>Provided by Siegfried Goeschl.</note>
        <note>Maven is a Java project management and project comprehension tool that
            provides a well defined model for your project. The Canoo WebTest plugin comes into
            play to model the acceptance tests. Typically Maven, that model is validated, run, and
            results get visualized.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="Jira" title="Jira" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://www.atlassian.com/software/jira/"/>
        <note>A Bug Tracking, Issue Tracking and Project Management Tool.</note>
        <note>Thanks to the atlassian people for providing such an
            excellent tool and for supporting Canoo WebTest with a free open source license.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="CLOVER" title="Clover" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://www.cenqua.com/clover/"/>
        <note>A code coverage tool for Java.</note>
        <note>Thanks to the clover people for providing such an
            excellent tool and for supporting Canoo WebTest with a free license.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="Intellij" title="IntelliJ IDEA" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://www.jetbrains.com/idea/"/>
        <note>An excellent Java, J2EE and XML (including WebTest scripts) refactoring IDE.</note>
        <note>Thanks to the JetBrains people for providing such an
            excellent tool and for supporting Canoo WebTest with a free open source license.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="OLS" title="Canoo Online Services" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://www.canoo.net"/>
        <note>The Canoo Online Services for german language exploration.</note>
        <note>Includes hundreds of pages with static, dynamic and mixed content.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="pdfbox" title="PDFBox" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://www.pdfbox.org"/>
        <note>PDFBox is a free open-source Java PDF Library developed by Ben Litchfield.</note>
        <author name="Ben Litchfield"/>
    </ref>
    <ref id="xls" title="XLS" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://office.microsoft.com/excel"/>
        <note>File format used by Microsoft Excel to save spreadsheets.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="pdf" title="PDF" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://www.adobe.com/products/acrobat/adobepdf.html"/>
        <note>Invented by Adobe, Portable Document Format (PDF) is the published specification
            used around the world for secure, reliable electronic document distribution and exchange.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="regex" title="regular expression" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4.2/docs/api/java/util/regex/Pattern.html"/>
        <note>Canoo WebTest uses the built in Regular Expression capacities of Java (since 1.4) with the dotall mode
            enabled (allows "." to match any character including a line terminator, this is what Perl names the single
            line mode).</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="XPATH" title="XPath" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xpath"/>
        <link href="http://www.w3schools.com/xpath/"/>
        <note>XML Path Language.</note>
        <note>XPath defines a formal notation to reference parts of XML document structures.
            Its main use is for XSLT and XPointer.</note>
        <note>XPath expressions allow to query a document like you would query a database
            by SQL. In combination with Canoo WebTest it enables queries on HTML documents.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="XPE" title="XPath Explorer" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://www.purpletech.com/xpe/index.jsp"/>
        <note>Alex Chaffee's XPath Exploration tool.</note>
        <note>It not only allows exploring XML/HTML using XPath, it also makes
            creating XPath expressions a real pleasure, as you can select the node under test
            and the expression will be created for you.</note>
        <note>The XPath Explorer is the recommended companion to use with WebTest's
            'verifyXPath' and 'storeXPath' steps.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="XPather" title="XPather" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://xpath.alephzarro.com/"/>
        <note>Firefox plugin to evaluate and generate XPath expressions while browsing.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="dbunit" title="DbUnit" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://dbunit.sourceforge.net/"/>
        <link href="http://dbunit.sourceforge.net/howto.html#canoo"/>
        <note>A tool for testing all database related issues.</note>
        <note>Beside testing your db queries and setup, it makes an excellent companion to
            WebTest as it allows to safely populate your test db with the required test data.
            Using the dbunit ANT task, this population can take place right before your
            test, such that WebTest and test data go together. (See also SQLUnit)</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="sqlunit" title="SQLUnit" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://sqlunit.sourceforge.net/"/>
        <link href="http://sqlunit.sourceforge.net/x3931.html"/>
        <note>A tool for testing all database related issues.</note>
        <note>Besides testing your db stored procedures, queries and setup, it makes an excellent
            companion to WebTest as it allows you to safely populate your test db with the required test data.
            Using the sqlunit ANT task, this population can take place right before your
            test, so that WebTest and the database test data are always in sync. Post test tidy up is also
            supported. SQLUnit supports reporting using an XML file compatible with WebTest's
            reporting format, so that you can generate HTML reports combining both sets of
            information. (See also DbUnit)</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="HTML" title="HTML" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://www.w3.org/MarkUp/"/>
        <note>Hypertext Markup Language.</note>
        <note>HTML is the lingua franca for publishing hypertext on the World Wide Web</note>
        <note>Consider visiting the site of the world wide web consortium to find more
            information about html variants, formats, parsers and validators.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="HTTP" title="HTTP" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://www.w3.org/Protocols/"/>
        <link href="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2616.txt"/>
        <note>Hypertext Transfer Protocol.</note>
        <note>The Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) is an application-level protocol for
            distributed, collaborative, hypermedia information systems. HTTP is used by browsers
            to request pages and images and submit forms. It is also used by RESTful Web Services
            to access services.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="validator" title="HTML Validator" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://validator.w3.org/"/>
        <link href="http://www.htmlhelp.com/tools/validator/"/>
        <link href="http://www.htmlvalidator.com/"/>
        <link href="http://arealvalidator.com/"/>
        <note>A program that checks whether an HTML page conforms to the standard.</note>
        <note>There are free validators on the web and commercial ones that can be run locally.</note>
        <note>Use one! It's worth it!</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="XML" title="XML" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://www.w3.org/xml"/>
        <note>Extensible Markup Language</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="xerces" title="Xerces" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://xerces.apache.org/xerces2-j/"/>
        <note>Apache Xerces XML Parser</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ibmPL" title="IBM Public License" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://oss.software.ibm.com/developerworks/opensource/license10.html"/>
        <note>IBM Public License conditions</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="XSLT" title="XSLT" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt"/>
        <link href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xsl/"/>
        <note>XSL Transformations</note>
        <note>Uses the Extensible Stylesheet Language (XSL) for transformations
            of XML trees into other tree structures like html, formatting objects
            (that can be serialized as PDF) or XML again.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="jakarta" title="The Jakarta Project" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/"/>
        <note>The leading Java open source software site.</note>
        <note>Includes the Apache web server, Tomcat, ANT, Log4J,
            Cactus, ORO, Struts and many more.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ANT" title="ANT" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://ant.apache.org/"/>
        <note>The leading build automation tool.</note>
        <note>The platform independent replacement for &quot;make&quot;.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ANTC" title="Ant-Contrib" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://ant-contrib.sourceforge.net/ant-contrib/manual/tasks/index.html"/>
        <note>The Ant-Contrib project is a collection of tasks (and at one point maybe types and other tools) for Apache
            Ant.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="BSF" title="Bean Scripting Framework (BSF)" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/bsf/"/>
        <note>Bean Scripting Framework (BSF) is a set of Java classes which
            provides scripting language support within Java applications.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="junit" title="JUnit" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://www.junit.org/"/>
        <note>Home of the unit test community.</note>
        <note>Points to articles, downloads and other on-line resources.</note>
        <note>Unit test tools for other languages than Java are also available,
            including Smalltalk, C++, Perl, Python, JavaScript and even VisualBasic.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="javascript" title="JavaScript" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/standards/Ecma-262.htm"/>
        <link href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/library/default.asp?url=/library/en-us/script56/html/js56jsoriJScript.asp"/>
        <link href="http://www.mozilla.org/js/"/>
        <note>The scripting language supported by most browsers.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="httpunit" title="HttpUnit" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://www.httpunit.org"/>
        <note>The Open Source Web Site Testing tool for programmers.</note>
        <note>Captures web site testing in JUnit TestCases.</note>
        <author name="Gold" firstname="Russell"/>
    </ref>
    <ref id="htmlunit" title="HtmlUnit" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://htmlunit.sourceforge.net/"/>
        <note>The Open Source java unit testing framework for testing web based applications.</note>
        <note>This is the "browser" used to play webtest test suites.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="groovy" title="Groovy" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://groovy.codehaus.org/"/>
        <note>Groovy is a powerful high-level scripting language for the Java platform
            which compiles down to Java bytecode and utilises Java syntax and features.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="jtidy" title="JTidy" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/jtidy"/>
        <note>Small and lean Open Source HTML parser.</note>
        <note>Is used in the HttpUnit package.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="nekohtml" title="NekoHTML" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://www.apache.org/~andyc/neko/doc/html/"/>
        <note>NekoHTML is a simple HTML scanner/parser and tag balancer that enables application programmers to
            parse HTML documents and access the information using standard XML interfaces.</note>
        <note>NekoHTML is used in the HtmlUnit package.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="jemmy" title="Jemmy" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://jemmy.netbeans.org/"/>
        <note>Jemmy is a library that is used to create automated tests for Java GUI applications.</note>
        <note>Is used in the AppletRunner step.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="jetty" title="Jetty" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://jetty.mortbay.org/jetty/"/>
        <note>Jetty is a 100% Java HTTP Server and Servlet Container.</note>
        <note>Is used to preform selftest in a controlled environment during the build of webtest.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="cruisecontrol" title="CruiseControl" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://cruisecontrol.sourceforge.net/"/>
        <note>The Open Source Continuous Integration facilitator.</note>
        <note>The site also points to more information about continuous integration.</note>
        <note>CruiseControl uses ANT to trigger new builds on any repository change
            and reports the build result as email and on a website using JSP, XML and XSLT.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ats" title="Automated Testing Specialists" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://www.sqa-test.com/"/>
        <note>Points to a huge set of resources about automated testing.</note>
        <note>Answers a lot of questions about testing.</note>
        <note>Homepage of an independent consultants&apos; community.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="sourceforge" title="SourceForge.net" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://sourceforge.net/"/>
        <note>The leading distribution page for open source software.</note>
        <note>A regular must-visit for every developer.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="canoo" title="Canoo Engineering AG" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://www.canoo.com/"/>
        <note>Owner of Canoo WebTest in Basel, Switzerland.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="seiberTEC" title="seiberTEC" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://www.seibertec.ch/"/>
        <note>A high-profile software development company in Rueschlikon, Switzerland.</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="cspb" title="Credit Suisse Private Banking" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://www.cspb.com/"/>
        <note>Credit Suisse Private Banking</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="csfs" title="Credit Suisse Financial Services" type="Home Page">
        <link href="http://www.csfs.com/"/>
        <note>Credit Suisse Fincancial Services</note>
    </ref>
    <ref id="data-driven" title="Totally Data-Driven Automated Testing" type="White Paper">
        <link href="http://www.sqa-test.com/w_paper1.html"/>
        <note>A must-read for the testing inclined developer.</note>
        <author name="Keith Zambelich">
            <occupation>Co-author of the WinRunner ATS Toolkit.</occupation>
            <occupation>Sr. Software Quality Assurance Analyst</occupation>
            <occupation>Automated Testing Evangelist</occupation>
        </author>
        <cite id="cost-effective">
            Record/Playback is the least cost-effective method of automating test cases.
        </cite>
    </ref>
    <ref id="pragmatic" title="The Pragmatic Programmer" type="Book">
        <link href="http://www.pragmaticprogrammer.com"/>
        <note>Addison-Wesley Oct 1999 ISBN: 020161622X</note>
        <note>It covers topics ranging from personal responsibility and
            career development to architectural techniques for keeping your code flexible,
            easy to adapt and reuse.
        </note>
        <author name="Hunt" firstname="Andrew"/>
        <author name="Thomas" firstname="David"/>
        <cite id="plain-text">
            The Power of Plain Text, section 14
        </cite>
        <cite>Design to Test.
            Start thinking about testing before you write a line of code.
        </cite>
        <cite>Test Early. Test Often. Test Automatically.
            Tests that run with every build are much more effective than test plans that sit on a shelf.
        </cite>
        <cite>
            Coding Ain&apos;t Done &apos;Til All the Tests Run.
        </cite>
        <cite>Find Bugs Once.
            Once a human tester finds a bug, it should be the last time a human tester finds that bug.
            Automatic tests should check for it from then on.
        </cite>
    </ref>
    <ref id="KatjaSchulze">
        <author name="K.S.">
            <occupation>Project Manager</occupation>
        </author>
        <cite id="ffo-success">
            Initially we used WebTest only for one of our applications that has the main focus on data entry.
            For the application has a quite complex data model and an elaborate business logic with many possible user
            roles,
            the usecase oriented tests tended to be very costly.
            We then were looking for a way to automate our manual tests and decided to use Canoo WebTest.
            After the initial effort for defining the testcases we had reproducable tests und furthermore an implicit
            documentation of the user processes. With the automation we also could parametrise the test cases,
            so that we became a kind of independent of the actual available test data.
            This lead to less effort for the software developers and faster test runs,
            what gave us a wider scope for covering special test cases.
            Based on these experiences it was decided to broaden the usage of WebTest in CSPB,
            on the one hand to more applications, on the other hand to more test levels.
            Now WebTest is used for business critical functions with several thousand users.
        </cite>
    </ref>
    <ref id="BryanDollery">
        <author name="Bryan Dollery">
            <occupation>Columnist at informIT</occupation>
        </author>
        <cite id="informit">
            Of course, the enlightened use HTML for all their human/computer interaction needs.
            It doesn't matter how you generate it - servlets, JSP, Struts, XML/XSLT, whatever - you're still
            going to have to test that front end.
            Common wisdom has it that HTTPUnit is fit for this task - but I disagree.
            HTTPUnit is a powerful and useful tool, but if you're just going to test HTML forms then I recommend Canoo
            WebTest.
            (..)
            The test script is in XML, and is extremely simple to write. A tag called invoke takes a URL as its
            parameter.
            This is a simple call to the web server.
            You can use tags such as verifyTitle, setInputField, getInputField, clickButton, and so on.
            It's all intuitively simple, and it works well.
        </cite>
    </ref>
    <ref id="RaibleDesigns">
        <author name="Matt Raible">
            <occupation>Web Technology Expert at www.raibledesigns.com</occupation>
        </author>
        <cite id="raibleDesigns">
            I used 2 very cool tools today.
            The first is Canoo's WebTest.
            (..)
            It's fricken sweet as you don't have to really write any code, and it just worked for me
            (..) my favorite feature in any software.
        </cite>
    </ref>
    <ref id="all">
        <author name="anonymous"/>
        <cite id="free-quality">
            Quality is for free, but only for those who are willing to pay heavily for it.
        </cite>
    </ref>
</references>
