<head title="Available PDF Steps">

    <b>This is the syntax documentation for the PDF steps.</b>

    <b>
        The PDF Steps allow various tests to be performed on PDF files that
        may be referenced by your web pages. There are steps which let you verify
        text content, verify fonts used, verify links, verify bookmarks,
        verify security information, verify form information and document metadata
        as well as various filters which allow you to further manipulate the extracted
        information.
    </b>

    <section title="Simple Usage Example">

        <b>
            <key>CWT</key> automatically stores away web pages that you visit as the current response.
            When you visit non-web page resources (such as PDFs) <key>CWT</key> doesn't automatically
            store away the response unless the <example>saveresponse</example>
            attribute of your <example>config</example> element is set to "true".
            The PDF document to test will then become the current response by invoking a URL that refers to your
            PDF document, or by submitting a form that will return the PDF document as its result, or by any other
            scenario that generates a request and has the PDF document as its response. Once the PDF document is
            available, you can perform different verifications on it using any of the available PDF or base steps.
        </b>

        <code caption="sampleSimpleUsageExample.xml">
            <include src='pdfexamples/sampleSimpleUsageExample.xml'/>
        </code>

    </section>

    <section title="Encrypted Document Example">

        <b>
            In order to test encrypted PDF documents you might want to decrypt it first. Otherwise,
            some content cannot be verified properly, e.g. AcroForm fields.
        </b>

        <code caption="sampleEncryptedUsageExample.xml">
            <include src='pdfexamples/sampleEncryptedUsageExample.xml'/>
        </code>

    </section>

    <section title="Debugging PDF documents">

        <b>
            Sometimes it is helpful to debug PDF documents on a very low-level.
            The included <em>pdfUnit</em> library comes with a Swing
            <em>PDF Object Browser</em> allowing low-level analysis of PDF documents.
        </b>

        <code>
            .../WEBTEST_HOME/lib/java -jar pdfUnit.jar
        </code>

        <b>
            Note that when you start the <em>PDF Object Browser</em>, the
            <em>log4j</em>, <em>pdfbox</em>, and <em>pdfUnit</em>
            libraries must all be in the same directory.
        </b>

    </section>

    <section title="Additional Setup Information">

        <b>
            You have three ways to incorporate the PDF steps into your tests:
            <dl>
                <li>
                    <dt>Import all steps approach:</dt>
                    <dd>
                        Simply use <example>&lt;import file="${webtest.home}/lib/taskdef.xml"/&gt;</example>
                        as illustrated in the <pageref name="Samples"/>.
                    </dd>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <dt>Specific plugins approach:</dt>
                    <dd>You can explicitly define the base and PDF tasks:<example>
                        &lt;taskdef resource="webtest_base_strict.taskdef" classpathref="webtest.all"
                                 loaderref="webtest.loader"/&gt;
                        &lt;taskdef resource="webtest_pdftest_relaxed.taskdef" classpathref="webtest.all"
                                 loaderref="webtest.loader"/&gt;
                    </example></dd>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <dt>Antlib approach:</dt>
                    <dd>You can use namespaces as follows:<example>
                        &lt;target xmlns:pdftest="antlib:com.canoo.webtest.plugins.pdftest" name="main"&gt;
                    </example>then simply refer to the steps using the namespace you defined, <em>pdftest</em>
                        in this case, e.g.<example>
                        &lt;pdftest:verifyPageCount count="1"/&gt;
                        &lt;pdftest:verifyText text="Some text on page"/&gt;
                    </example>Note that the <em>pdf</em> prefix is stripped off any tasks starting with <em>pdf</em>.</dd>
                </li>
            </dl>
        </b>
    </section>

</head>