<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE manpage SYSTEM "manpage.dtd" [
<!ENTITY site                       SYSTEM "WebTestSite.xml">
<!ENTITY dumpDOM             "<include src='examples/dumpDOM.xml' />">
<!ENTITY debuggingWebConnection             "<include src='examples/debuggingWebConnection.xml' />">
<!ENTITY taskdef					      "<include src='examples/taskdef.xml' />">
]>

<manpage siteid="Troubleshooting">

&site;

<head title="Troubleshooting WebTests">

</head>
    <section title="Issue Tracker">
        <b>
            When in trouble, you may want to visit Canoo WebTest's
            <ext base="jira" href="">JIRA Issue Tracker</ext>.
        </b>
    </section>

    <section title="Out of Memory">
		<b>
			<key>ANT</key> may eat up a lot of memory when started for
            the use with Canoo WebTest. You can give it more space to live
            in by specifying a higher "maximum heap size" through the
            environment variable <example>ANT_OPTS</example>, e.g.:
		</b>
		<b>
			<example>ANT_OPTS=-Xmx128m</example>
		</b>
		<b>
			See the <key>ANT</key> documentation for more details.
		</b>
		<b>
			In order to save memory avoid calling the
            <example>taskdef</example> more than once. When your test suite
            grows beyond some thousand steps consider using
            more than one file for collecting the reports.
		</b>
	</section>

	<section title="java.lang.VerifyError">
		<b>
			There may be non-compliant <key>ANT</key> version that
			interferes with the <example>ant.jar</example>
			provided in <example>&lt;WEBTESTHOME&gt;/lib</example>.
		</b>
		<b>
			Consider to copy <example>&lt;WEBTESTHOME&gt;/lib/ant.jar</example>
			to <example>&lt;ANT_HOME&gt;/lib</example>.
		</b>
		<b>
			While <example>installTest.xml</example> reports this error
			on some occasions, it cannot catch all possible cases.
		</b>
	</section>

	<section title="Parsing issues">

		<b>If it happens for instance that Canoo WebTest shows an error indicating that it
		did not find a button that was referenced in a test although the button
		is clearly visible in the browser (and works as well), one of the most
		common reasons is incorrectly formatted <key>HTML</key> that isn't understood
		by the parser.
		</b>

		<b>"Normal" browsers are able to cope with really messy <key>HTML</key> code.
		WebTest too.. but not to the same extend.
		</b>
		
		<b>An <key>validator</key> will be able to tell you if your HTML code is valid or not
		and indicate how to fix it.
		</b>

		<b>To "see" the current state of a page (the DOM) in memory, you can dump it to the console
		with a small step:
		</b>
		<code caption="Dump current DOM to the console">
			&dumpDOM;
		</code>

	</section>

	<section title="JavaScript Errors">

	<b>
		There are two types of JavaScript errors: "real" JavaScript errors occurring as well in a "real" browser and JavaScript errors
		occurring only in WebTest due to insufficient/incorrect reproduction of the simulated browser's behavior.
	</b>
	<b>
		If your test fails due to a "real" JavaScript error, it is wise to fix your application. If you can't do it, you can
		choose to ignore JavaScript errors.
	</b>
	<b>
		Following steps may help to understand the cause of a JavaScript error reported by WebTest:
		</b>
			<dl>
				<li>
					<dt>Verify in the "real" browser</dt>
					<dd>The quality of the browser simulation including JavaScript execution is already very good and it often happens
					that WebTest reports exactly the same JavaScript errors than the simulated browser (sometimes even with a better precision!).
					To detect if you have encountered a real JavaScript error, you need to do exactly the same actions in your browser
					than the ones done in your webtest. This requires high concentration! Be sure to really click the same links and buttons
					as your WebTest and not any other than may appear in the page (even with same label).
					In Firefox you can see JavaScript errors for instance in the JavaScript console. Other browsers have similar ways to acces
					to JavaScript errors.  
					</dd>
				</li>
				<li>
					<dt>Ugrade to latest WebTest and HtmlUnit version</dt>
					<dd>If no error occurs in the real browser that you want to simulate with your webtest, then it probably means that
					WebTest's behavior is incorrect. Be sure to use the latest WebTest build (replacing as well the HtmlUnit
					version contained in WebTest by the latest HtmlUnit snapshot when possible): it's possible that the problem you encounter
					has already been fixed.
					</dd>
				</li>
				<li>
					<dt>Report the problem</dt>
					<dd>If the problem still occurs with the most recent versions of WebTest (and HtmlUnit) then it means that you've
					hint a new problem. In this case, please report it. Problems are sometimes fixed within a very short time.
					A look at HtmlUnit's <ext href="http://htmlunit.sourceforge.net/submittingJSBugs.html">Submitting JavaScript bugs</ext>
					documentation may help to find the best way to report a bug.
					</dd>
				</li>
			</dl>
    </section>
    
    	<section title="Button found more than once">

	<b>For clicking on a button or a link, Canoo WebTest needs to locate that
	button or that link on the page. The above message occurs if the reference
	is not unique, which generally indicates an error in the test.</b>

	<b>Consider using the <example>name</example> attribute or a locator element
	to create a unique reference. Refer to the syntax description and the samples
	on how to do this.</b>

	<b>If the message still shows up, although the reference should be unique,
	it is likely that the page's <key>HTML</key> source is invalid. A common
	error is improper nesting of <example>form</example> elements with
	table rows and cells, they cannot be mixed.
	<sectionref number="4"/> may be helpful.</b>

	</section>
	
	<section title="Inspect HTTP traffic">

	<b>
		It is sometimes interesting to inspect the HTTP traffic to compare 
		the requests sent by WebTest and the responses received from the server(s)
		when WebTest is running with the ones of the "real" browser being simulated.
		Caution: remember that WebTest will do less requests than a normal browser, for instance
		it won't download images and stylesheets unless it detects that they play a role in the
		JavaScript execution.
	</b>
	<b>
		There are different solutions to view the HTTP traffic, for instance these ones:
	</b>
		<dl>
			<li>
				<dt>Use DebuggingWebConnection in WebTest</dt>
				<dd>
				Following code instruments the web connection of the underlying
				<example>WebClient</example>. This will generate 
				a report of the HTTP traffic in the sub-folder named <example>mytest</example>
				of your temporary directory for the rest of your webtest:
					<code caption="Wrap HTMLUnit web connection to track HTTP traffic">
						&debuggingWebConnection;
					</code>
				</dd>
			</li>
			<li>
				<dt>Use Firebug in Firefox</dt>
				<dd>
				The Network monitoring features of the <ext href="www.getfirebug.com/">Firebug</ext> extension for Firefox
				allow to track all HTTP requests.
				</dd>
			</li>
			<li>
				<dt>Use a proxy both for WebTest and your "normal" browser</dt>
				<dd>
				An other solution to track HTTP traffic both for WebTest and for a "normal" browser
				is to use an HTTP proxy that can show you the request and responses.
				Different proxies are available for this purpose. For Java developers
				<ext href="http://www.parosproxy.org/index.shtml">Paros</ext> may be interesting
				as it is Open Source and written in Java.
				</dd>
			</li>
		</dl>
	</section>

	<section title="Getting more information">

	<b>A test fails, but you don't know why? If that is because of the <key>ANT</key>
	structure of the tests, unresolved properties or unexpected directory handling, you
	should consider running your <key>ANT</key> tests with the <example>-v</example>
	option. This gives additional verbose information about target sequence, unresolved
	properties and attempts to override property values.</b>

	<b>If it is a problem within the <key>HTML</key>, try to use the reporting as described
	in <sectionref number="2"/>. It is often useful to inspect your page
	with an <key>validator</key>.</b>

	</section>
	<section title="Debugging WebTest">

	<b>The last ditch attempt to troubleshoot Canoo WebTest is to go for Java debugging
	on the source code level. You are likely to need not only the Canoo WebTest sources
	but also the source of the packages that Canoo WebTest is built on. That is <key>ANT</key>,
	and <key>htmlunit</key>. You may need even more, e.g. when
	stepping into the HTML parsing. But if you are so experienced, you probably know
	how to do this.</b>

	<b>You need a Java debugger, a class to start the debugger on, the command line parameters and
	the proper classpath and sourcepath. We cannot help you with the debugger itself. You
	probably have one within your IDE. The JDK contains the <example>jdb</example>, but that one
	is not very comfortable. The remaining parameters can be determined from your ant starter
	script that resides under <example>&lt;ANT_HOME&gt;/bin</example>. Put all jars on the
	<example>CLASSPATH</example> that reside under <example>&lt;ANT_HOME&gt;/lib</example>
	and <example>&lt;WEBTESTHOME&gt;/lib</example>. Put the sources on the
	<example>-sourcepath</example>.
	Provide the option
	<example>-Dant.home="&lt;ANT_HOME&gt;"</example> and start the debugger on the class
	<example>org.apache.tools.ant.Main</example>. Provide the command line parameters
	<example>-buildfile &lt;file&gt;</example> and <example>&lt;target&gt;</example> as
	necessary.</b>

	<b>When debugging, a good thing to look for is implicit tags that the parser
	inserts into incomplete <key>HTML</key>.</b>

	</section>
	<section title="Tests get messy">

	<b>If your tests get messy, this is mostly because they contain duplication. Avoid
	this at any costs.</b>

	<b>Put all the references that occur more than once into an <key>ANT</key> property.
	Consider putting shared properties into a properties file. Use the
	<example>ant</example> and <example>antcall</example> tasks to
	extract reusable logic into subbuild files and subtargets. Use <key>XML</key>
	entities for textual includes. See the samples on how to do this. Also
    consider using Macros - see the <key>ANT</key> documentation for more details.</b>

	<b>Keep your targets short and avoid putting too many <example>webtest</example>s
	into one target. </b>

	<b>Make use of the <example>description</example> attribute for main targets and
	use the <example>description</example> attribute for test steps.</b>

	</section>
	<section title="Weird Errors running your script">

	<b>
        If you get weird errors when running your script inside an IDE it could be that
        your IDE is using a custom ant runner. For some reason this seems to sometimes
        cause a conflict. If you find yourself in this situation, try to configure
        your IDE to use a standard <key>ANT</key> runner.
    </b>

    <b>
        Possible technical explanation: <key>CWT</key>
        relies on <key>htmlunit</key> which parses <key>HTML</key> using <key>nekohtml</key>.
        <key>nekohtml</key> is set up as a custom ContentHandler for the <key>xerces</key> XML Parser.
        Your custom <key>ANT</key> runner may also have set itself up as a custom ContentHandler.
        For some reason this seems to sometimes cause a conflict.
    </b>

    <b>
        As an example, in IntelliJ, if you run a script which uses the standard embedded ant
        then if you have a step which parses HTML you might see the following exception thrown:
        <example>java.lang.AbstractMethodError: org.cyberneko.html.HTMLScanner.getCharacterOffset()I</example>.
        This will occur if you for instance use an <stepref name="invoke" category="core"/> step.
        The workaround is simply to configure
        in your ant build settings to use an external ant rather than the embedded one.
    </b>

    </section>


</manpage>